בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Sunday. בוקר... Boker... okay, בוקר טוב. Boker tov.
Today's דף daf is כ"ז Chaf-Zayin 27. We pick up at the
two dots of כ"ו עמוד ב'. Chaf-Vav Amud Bet.
Yesterday had been a nice conclusion about the issues about הנאה hana'ah
with the discussion about when somebody is deriving benefit not through an
action but it just comes upon them and how whether כוונה kavanah
just what's going on in your head would make that forbidden or
not. And in the course of that we also touched on a
very important question about whether what types of things even constitute הנאה,
hana'ah, aesthetic קול, kol, מראה... mareh... I mean מראה, mareh, excuse me,
קול, kol, auditory and those are not biblical הנאה, hana'ah, might be
rabbinically still a problem and then ריח, rei'ach, smell, which is considered
a problem as something that is more considered to be actually substantive
and physical. We continue now today also with a related to the
הנאה hana'ah issue at the two dots ולא יסיק בו, velo yasik
bo, returning to the משנה mishna that said one of the things
you cannot do with חמץ chametz is to use it to heat
up an oven. You're burning the חמץ chametz and you want to
heat up an oven and bake bread in the oven, bake bread,
bake מצה matzah let's say, bake chicken, cook chicken in the oven,
you can't do that because you are it's a form of deriving
benefit. ולא יסיק בו תנו רבנן. Velo yasik bo tano rabbanan. So
let's look at the גמרא, Gemara, תנו
רבנן tanu rabbanan our Rabbis taught, תנור שהסיקו בקליפי ערלה tannur shehisiko
biklipei orlah if you now this is a parallel discussion remember now
because of the previous discussion we know a couple of things that
are אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah and two of them are ערלה orlah
and כלאיים. kilayim. We could also talk about שור הנסקל shor haniskal
but we won't. But anyway, so you have a תנור, tannur, you
have an oven שהסיקו בקליפי ערלה shehisiko biklipei orlah that you fired
it up with shells from ערלה orlah from you know within the
first three years of the fruit. או בקשים של כלאי הכרם O
be'kashim shel kilei hakerem or with the like the straw you know
that
of like the vines of something that grew as כלאיים. kilayim. So
you're using wood from something that's אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah to heat
up a to fire up an oven.
חדש יוצד, Chadash yutzad, ישן יוצד. yashan yutzad. If it's a new
oven then the first firing up of a new oven basically serves
as a type of a kiln. It's like taking this pottery because
the oven was made out of pottery and firing it up and
hardening it. So therefore you now have a oven that was hardened
by איסורי הנאה. issurei hana'ah. And the assumption is that the next
time I use this oven will be considered deriving benefit from איסורי
הנאה. issurei hana'ah. Now that's interesting because you could have said no,
the prohibition I did was when I fired up the oven and
then I got benefit I improved my oven. From this point on
the איסורי הנאה issurei hana'ah is no longer around, I'm just deriving
benefit from my oven. But this but this position assumes that the
continued use of the oven is a continued indirect deriving benefit from
that איסורי הנאה issurei hana'ah because you would not have been able
to be cooking your chicken now were it not that you had
first hardened your oven with these איסורי הנאה issurei hana'ah so you
are continuing to derive benefit from the איסורי הנאה. issurei hana'ah.
It's like a גמר מלאכה, gmar melacha, גמר מעשה, gmar ma'aseh, it
actually fashions the oven.
Right. This fashions the oven but then the חידוש chiddush is though
that every continued use is a continued a continued deriving of benefit
of benefit, right. The איסורי הנאה issurei hana'ah has not has not
left the scene. Okay, so ישן yashan now if it's an old
oven then you don't have a problem using the oven per se
after this but you can't use the current fire because the current
fire is coming from these איסורי הנאה issurei hana'ah so יוצן yutzan
you let it cool off but then you can use it again
as long as you make a new fire. אפה בו את הפת
Afah bo et hapat now let's say you actually went ahead and
baked bread in it this is now not about פסח Pesach this
is ערלה. orlah. So you baked bread in this oven so presumably
let's say the oven that still had the fire going from the
איסורי הנאה. issurei hana'ah.
So רבי אומר הפת אסורה Rebbi omer hapat asurah you cannot derive
benefit from the bread. It makes a lot of sense if you
can't derive benefit from the oven if it was hardened then you
certainly you know you would assume you also couldn't derive benefit from
the bread that was baked with איסורי הנאה. issurei hana'ah. וחכמים אומרים
Vechachamim omrim but the sages say no הפת מותרת hapat muteret that
you might that you might have transgressed when you baked the bread
but now that the bread is already bread is already baked you
do not transgress again when you actually eat the bread. So logically
you would assume that they should say the same thing about the
oven as well that if even if you hardened the oven once
what you did is over with you could be you you no
longer continue to transgress and we will see the גמרא Gemara will
make that connection.
And how far do you go with these things? Like let's say
it's a cold day and I know that there's קליפי ערלה klipei
orlah in here. Right. Am I allowed to stay in the room?
Like you know or let's say the ערלה orlah fell on my
field and you know it's going to fertilize it. Do I have
to actually get rid of it?
Well there's a question about passive if it happened by itself that
I mean what you're really raising are similar questions about אפשר ולא
מכוון, efshar velo kemechaven, okay? So if that's a different question but
here we're defining what constitutes הנאה, hana'ah, okay? You have to combine
the two סוגיות sugyot to get an answer to your question. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this: בישרא אגבי גחלי. Bishra Agavi Gechali.
Now let's say the fire is no longer a raging fire but
it's turned into coals, and now you cooked your bread on top
of the coals. In that case, דברי הכל מותר, Divrei Hakol Mutar,
everybody says it's permissible. Why? Because then the ערלה Orlah and the
כלאים Kilayim is already destroyed if it's turned into coals, and what's
left, the ashes and the coals of completely burnt wood, is no
longer ערלה Orlah and כלאים. Kilayim. So in that case, not only
should it perhaps be מותר Mutar בדיעבד Bedi'avad to bake to use
the bread, you might even לכתחילה L'chatchila be allowed to bake the
bread once it has completely turned into coals. Now the רן Ran
points out, this is not as obvious as it would seem because
we actually have this question about when does איסורי הנאה Issurei Hana'ah
lose its status? And this came up in the past and the
גמרא Gemara will say it at the end of today's דף. Daf.
The principle is כל הנסרפים אפרן מותר, Kol Hanisrapim Afaran Mutar, כל
הנקברים אפרן אסור. Kol Hanikbarim Afaran Assur.
I mentioned this the other day because one of the principles we
learned yesterday was this idea of נעשית מצותו. Na'aseit Mitzvato. Once a
מצוה Mitzvah is done to something it loses its status, and I
pointed out yesterday that that could mean two ways. If the thing
is off limits because of the מצוה, Mitzvah, like it's a קורבן
Korban or something, then once the מצוה Mitzvah is done, though, it
stops being off limits. But even something that's not that way, even
something that's off limits because it's אסור בהנאה, Assur Behana'ah, like כלאים,
Kilayim, כלאי הכרם. Kilai Hakerem. If the תורה Torah says פן תקדש
Pen Tikdash and the גמרא's Gemara דרשה Drasha פן תקדש Pen Tikdash
is תוקד אש, Tukad Aish,
that the מצוה Mitzvah is to burn the כלאים, Kilayim, once you've
done what you're supposed to do with it, you've destroyed, burnt it,
then it loses its status, it becomes permissible. So that's why נסרפים
אפרן מותר. Nisrapim Afaran Mutar. If you're supposed to burn it and
you burnt it, then it loses its status, it becomes permissible. However,
there are things that are אסור בהנאה, Assur Behana'ah, like let's say
a שור הנסקל, Shor Haniskal, that it doesn't say to burn it.
So even if it's נקברים, Nikbarim, you would bury it to get
rid of it, to get it out of the way, but there's
no מצוה Mitzvah to do something with it. And therefore even if
you chose to burn it, it would retain its status because there's
no particular thing you're supposed to do with this, so the act
of burning doesn't make it lose its status. So the רן Ran
points out that we're talking specifically here about כלאים Kilayim and ערלה
Orlah where there's a מצוה Mitzvah to burn them. Other איסורי הנאה
Issurei Hana'ah might not be the same, even חמץ בפסח Chametz B'Pesach
we'll talk about whether that's a מצוה Mitzvah to burn or to
destroy in other ways.
But but but these כלאים Kilayim and ערלה Orlah that there's a
מצוה Mitzvah to burn it, so the משנה Mishna says once or
the ברייתא Braita says once you've burned it, then it becomes totally
permissible, so once it turns into coal, then you can actually use
it. So כלאים, Kilayim, I said there's a דרשה Drasha of פן
תקדש, Pen Tikdash, תוקד אש. Tukad Aish. Okay, חז''ל Chazal learn it
out. It's not necessarily explicit in the פסוקים. Psukim.
You're talking about כלאי הכרם.
Kilai Hakerem. Not not like if it's כלאים. Kilayim. No no no,
כלאי הכרם, Kilai Hakerem, not כלאי זרעים. Kilai Zraim. Okay, so that
I just want to point out that the last line here that
it's permissible once it becomes ashes or coal is not necessarily obvious,
but it's true here because there is a מצוה Mitzvah to burn
these.
Is this because of the outcome, it's a דבר חדש Davar Chadash
by it becoming גחלים, Gechalim, or לאו דוקא, Lav Davka, it doesn't
matter, it's that you did the action that's been prescribed by the
תורה Torah to transform? Right, so so let's say it didn't turn
into גחלים Gechalim but you burnt it.
Right, so that's a good question. I mean I would say on
the one hand, actually the phrase you used דבר חדש, Davar Chadash,
תוספות Tosafot in one place says the reason that כל הנסרפים אפרן
מותר, Kol Hanisrapim Afaran Mutar, תוספות Tosafot says is פנים חדשות באו
לכאן. Panim Chadashot Ba'u L'chan.
But that on the one hand, making it something new is not
sufficient in itself, like if the you burnt a שור הנסקל, Shor
Haniskal, the fact that it's a new piece of coal does not
in itself make it permissible. It has to be this case of
you've done the מצוה. Mitzvah.
The general answer is I'm not sure that a gap actually exists.
The מצוה Mitzvah to burn it means to burn it to a
point that it's no longer recognizable.
In hypothetically, were there a מצוה Mitzvah to burn it that you
would be יוצא Yotze before
and the thing would still be recognizable and not totally transformed, in
principle you're right, it would be מותר. Mutar. Consider for example the
idea of זריקת הדם Zrikat Hadam by the מזבח. Mizbe'ach. Now that's
not איסורי הנאה, Issurei Hana'ah, as I said that's a slightly different
category, but once you've זורק Zorek the דם, Dam, it looks the
same but it still becomes מותר Mutar because of נעשית מצותו. Na'aseit
Mitzvato. So in principle were a gap to exist, נעשית מצותו Na'aseit
Mitzvato is sufficient to make it permissible.
And is this also quickly, why is it שבח עצים? Shevach Etzim?
In other words, why is it שבח עצים? Shevach Etzim?
Well, we haven't even gotten to that phrase so you're ahead of
us. Okay, so so the גמרא Gemara says like this: בישרא אגבי
גחלי דברי הכל מותר. Bishra Agavi Gechali Divrei Hakol Mutar. So the
גמרא Gemara says והתניא, Vehatanya, okay, so that's separate. והתניא, Vehatanya, did
not teach in another ברייתא, Braita, however, בין חדש בין ישן יוצן,
Bein Chadash Bein Yashan Yutzan, that an old and a new one
you let them cool, so you can't benefit from the fire while
it's raging, but the oven itself is permissible, even a new oven.
So clearly there's a debate of what's the status of the oven
that was fired with איסורי הנאה? Issurei Hana'ah? So the גמרא Gemara
says לא קשיא, Lo Kashya, it's not a problem. הא רבי הא
רבנן, Ha Rebbi Ha Rabbanan, it's actually yeah, it's a debate of
תנאים. Tannaim. Now remember רבי Rebbi said that you can't eat the
bread, even
בדיעבד. Bedi'avad. the wood indirectly. So the גמרא gemara says that position
would also say you can't continue to use the oven if it
was a new oven because once you fire the... the oven is
like the bread, you benefited from having the fire in the oven,
it hardened the oven, so to continue to use the oven would
be to continue to benefit indirectly from the wood. So we have
two opinions, we have a debate in these ברייתות baraitot whether can
you use the oven that was hardened, the new oven that was
hardened by איסורי הנאה. issurei hana'ah. גמרא gemara says yeah, it's the
same debate of רבי rabbi and the חכמים chachamim whether you can
use the bread that was baked with איסורי הנאה. issurei hana'ah. Is
it considered like you are continuing to derive benefit after that first
act? So the גמרא gemara says it's fine, it's a debate of
תנאים, tannaim, we already see it by the bread. So the גמרא
gemara says no, one minute. The גמרא gemara says
אימא דשמעת ליה לרבי, eima de-shamat lei le-rabbi, when did you hear
that רבי rabbi said that the bread is a problem? משום דיש
שבח עצים בפת, mishum de-yesh shevach eitzim be-pat, because the benefit of
the wood still exists in the bread. Right, what the wood has
contributed, it baked the bread, so there's some wood value still in
the bread. Okay, so and that's why you can't eat the bread.
But זה וזה גורם מי שמעת ליה, zeh va-zeh gorem mi-shamat lei,
but it wouldn't necessarily be the same as the oven. Why not?
Because when you use the oven, you're using the oven together with
the fire. You don't directly benefit from the oven itself. If you
basically stored your bread in the oven, you used your oven as
a storage cabinet, then using the oven would be like using the
bread. Again, this is a new oven that it now is hard
because of the fire. But when you use the oven, you don't
use it as a storage cabinet, you use it to bake more
bread. Well, you're using it together with the fire. So you are
actually, the benefit you're getting out of it is a זה וזה
גורם, zeh va-zeh gorem, it's two things are contributing to the benefit
you're getting right now when you're baking your bread a second time.
The oven is contributing and the fire is contributing. And this is
a classic question the גמרא gemara asks, which is: what is the
story about זה וזה גורם? zeh va-zeh gorem? When two things contribute,
does the fact that one of them is problematic make it all
a problem, or does the fact that one of them is okay
means what I'm not getting it all from the other one, from
the bad one, so it's not such a bad... it's not so
bad. Okay, now obviously we're dealing that the problematic thing is not
there by itself. For example, if I... well, you know, I won't
describe it too much, we'll see cases. So that's... so that's basically
the גמרא's gemara position. Yes, רבי rabbi says that once the bread
was baked, the problem is still in the bread and you can't
continue to benefit from the bread. And yes, he would say there's
a problem in the oven, but that doesn't mean he would say
you can't bake in the oven because when you're going to bake
in the oven, both the oven and the fire will contribute to
the bread and the oven won't be the only contributor and maybe
that won't be a problem. Maybe that won't consider like I derived
benefit, forbidden benefit, because A, it's indirect, right? It's the wood made
the oven and the oven helped me bake the bread. And even
though normally that indirect is a problem for me, would say רבי,
rabbi, but it's also being done by the fire as well. It's
not all coming from the oven and maybe I would not see
that as a problem. Yes.
That oven could never be good after that, even though a different
wood?
That is the position of the ברייתא, baraita, which is if it
was a new oven that was finished by the fire, you have
to destroy it.
You just get rid of it. So all these other questions really
don't hold? If the oven should have been destroyed, then you're not
baking more bread in it.
Well, that's the question, but the גמרא gemara says that רבי, rabbi,
that's the גמרא's gemara point, it says the ברייתא, baraita, the first
ברייתא baraita says that if you baked more bread, רבי rabbi says
it's a problem and the חכמים chachamim say it's not. But the
question is would רבי rabbi go further to say you should... you
know, you shouldn't have even used the oven to begin with. You
should have broken it? Yeah, you didn't, you baked the bread. So
רבי rabbi says the bread is a problem.
Right, what רבי rabbi says, I'm sorry, I... when רבי rabbi says
if you bake the bread, the bread is a problem, that's even
in an old oven. That's when you bake the bread with the
fire that was of wood of איסורי הנאה. issurei hana'ah.
But you can continue to use the oven with different wood?
If it was an old oven, you could continue to use it.
Would רבי rabbi who says the bread is a problem when it
was an old oven say the oven is a problem when it
was a new oven and you have to destroy the oven for
all future uses? Right.
So the question is if you did not break that new oven
that was hardened with the forbidden wood and then you baked bread
the next day with permitted wood... right... what do you do with
that bread? You should have broken the oven, you didn't.
Right, or even before you get to the bread, am I allowed
to bake in this oven a second time? Is the act of
baking considered the same as the act of eating the bread is
considered continuing to benefit? continuing to benefit from איסורי הנאה. issurei hana'ah.
Is the act of baking in this new oven after it was
fired up considered continuing to benefit or do we say no I'm
not benefiting? A, it's indirect and B, there's another contributor, which is
the fire. So that's the question. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this. זה
וזה גורם משמיה zeh v'zeh gorem mishmeih who heard that he ever
said that when there are two contributors, it's a problem? So we
still don't know, we can't assume that רבי Rebbi that's strict by
the bread would be strict by the oven. So the גמרא Gemara
says אלא לא קשיא הא רבי אליעזר הא רבנן. ela lo kashya
ha Rabi Eliezer ha rabanan. Fine. You want to know the person
that says the opinion that זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh gorem is
a problem? It's רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. דתנן d'tnan
היי רבי אליעזר? hai Rabi Eliezer? Which רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer? אילימא
רבי אליעזר דשאור. ilima Rabi Eliezer d'seor. There's a רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer by yeast. Now this is not by חמץ, chametz, this is
by a different concern. דתנן d'tnan let's take a look at the
משנה.
Mishnah. Yeast is sourdough.
Sourdough really. שאור של חולין seor shel chullin if you have sourdough
of non-תרומה, terumah, חולין. chullin. ושל תרומה v'shel terumah and sourdough of
תרומה. terumah. שנפלו לתוך עיסה. shenaflo l'toch issah. And they fell into
a dough. Okay. Now the point is that even if תרומה terumah
is not enough quantity to create a problem, if it has the
effect of fermenting, then it makes the whole bread like תרומה. terumah.
It's sort of like you know the principle for example about מעמיד,
mamid, right? Everyone knows like gelatin is an issue because even if
it's small in quantity, if it gives form to the thing it's
a part of, if it hardens it, there's a principle called like
דבר המעמיד davar hamamid when it has its larger effect. So even
if you have a tiny bit of sourdough and it's enough to
be בטל batel by quantity, if it causes the bread to ferment,
then it is considered still to be present. So let's say there
was not enough תרומה terumah to cause the dough to ferment, but
in combination with a little sourdough of תרומה terumah and a little
sourdough of חולין, chullin, in combination they were enough to cause the
dough to ferment. Would it be considered like the תרומה terumah is
still present? That's the question. So that's a זה וזה גורם. zeh
v'zeh gorem. By itself it didn't cause the fermenting, but it did
it together with the חולין. chullin.
דבר המעמיד davar hamamid with the gelatin is an issue though also
of whether it's דבר חדש. davar chadash.
You have to decide whether gelatin is itself a problem, correct. Right.
Okay. For sure. Exactly. Okay, דתנן: d'tnan: שאור של חולין ושל תרומה
שנפלו לתוך עיסה. seor shel chullin v'shel terumah shenaflo l'toch issah. So
a little bit of sourdough of each fell into the dough. ואין
בזה כדי להחמיץ ואין בזה כדי להחמיץ. v'ein b'zeh k'dei l'hachmitz v'ein
b'zeh k'dei l'hachmitz. Neither on its own is enough to cause it
to ferment. וניצטרפו וחימצו. v'nitztarfu v'chimtzu.
And they joined together and they were מחמיץ. machmitz. That's what you
know partnership, a little working together. So anyway, sorry. So they joined
together and they caused it to be מחמיץ machmitz the dough. וניצטרפו
וחימצו. v'nitztarfu v'chimtzu. So וחימצו. v'chimtzu.
רבי אליעזר אומר אחר אחרון אני בא. Rabi Eliezer omer achar acharon
ani ba. I say that whatever fell in last, that determines. Okay,
because if they fell in sequentially, whatever happened first is over and
done with, and the thing that caused it to ferment was the
thing that fell in last, because otherwise you had non-fermenting dough. We'll
talk about that later. Non-fermenting dough, and this last thing fell in
and caused it to ferment, so you focus on the last thing.
וחכמים אומרים בין שנפל איסור בתחילה בין שנפל איסור לבסוף v'chachamim omrim
bein shenafal issur b'tchilah bein shenafal issur l'basof whether the איסור issur
fell in at the beginning or the end. לעולם אינו אסור עד
שיהא בו כדי להחמיץ. l'olam eino assur ad she-yehei bo k'dei l'hachmitz.
That it's not doing it by itself, it's doing it together with
the חולין, chullin, so the תרומה terumah itself is never doing it
all alone and therefore זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh gorem is מותר.
mutar. So I don't care first or last, it's not doing it
by itself, it's not a problem. Now even now it's not clear
that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh gorem
is אסור assur because he talked about it being sequential. Right. So
let's take a look at
אביי. Abaye. אביי Abaye says about this: לא שנו אלא שקדם וסילק
את האיסור. lo shanu ela she-kadam v'silek et ha-issur. When did רבי
Rebbi when did רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer say that the איסור issur
has to be last? That's if the איסור issur fell in first
and you removed it and then the היתר heter fell in. Then
you could say the איסור issur was doing nothing because it's already
been removed, and that's why he would say it would be okay.
אבל לא קדם וסילק את האיסור aval lo kadam v'silek et ha-issur
but if you didn't do that, if they're both present at the
same time, even if they fell in sequentially, and certainly if they
fell in sequentially, אסור assur it would be forbidden. So he reinterprets
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer to say the only reason רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer is lenient is you removed the איסור. issur. But as long
as the איסור issur is there, it's a problem, even though it's
not doing it by itself. So according to אביי, Abaye, רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer is of the position זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh gorem
if two things are contributing, it still is a problem. So אלמא
זה וזה גורם אסור almah zeh v'zeh gorem assur you see if
this and this contribute, it's still a problem. So that would be
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer would presumably hold the same position by the
oven. So the גמרא Gemara says וממאי דטעמיה דרבי אליעזר כדאביי? u-mimai
d'ta'ameih d'Rabi Eliezer k'd'Abaye? What makes you think the reasoning of רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is like אביי? Abaye? This is quite fascinating, right,
because the גמרא Gemara normally just takes for granted if an אמורא
Amora interprets a תנא, Tanna, that must be what the תנא Tanna
means. But here the גמרא Gemara is saying who says אביי Abaye
is right? That's not necessarily what רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is saying.
דילמא טעמיה דרבי אליעזר משום דאחר אחרון אני בא. dilma ta'ameih d'Rabi
Eliezer mishum d'achar acharon ani ba. Maybe
what a crazy idea, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is... Because everybody says
that even if the איסור issur is still there, you focus on
the last one, and it's not an issue of זה וזה גורם,
zeh v'zeh gorem, it's an issue of the last one.
It's very unusual that
some of the lawyers, I know, right? The layers, exactly, exactly.
לא שנא קדם וסלק את האיסור, lo shena qadam v'sillaq et ha'issur,
it doesn't matter if you remove the איסור issur first, לא שנא
לא קדם וסלק את האיסור, lo shena lo qadam v'sillaq et ha'issur,
even if you didn't remove the איסור issur first, even if it's
still there, as long as it wasn't the last one, maybe it's
okay. אבל בבת אחת, aval b'vat achas, if they fell in together,
הכא נמי דשרי, hacha nami d'shari, and maybe he would say as
long as the איסור issur is not the last one, זה וזה
גורם zeh v'zeh gorem is not a problem to me, and if
it's sitting around there, the איסור, issur, or even at the same
time, it would be okay. So you cannot prove that רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer says זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh gorem is a problem.
אלא, Ella, okay, we'll try a different רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. רבי
אליעזר דעצי אשרה, Rabbi Eliezer d'atzei Asherah, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer of
the
אשרה Asherah wood, right? We're talking about a lot of concepts that
we normally wouldn't talk about in פסחים Pesachim and they're constantly coming
up again and again. So אשרה Asherah we mentioned, I mean, you're
talking about איסורי הנאה, issurei hana'ah, these things are going to be
revisited. So we're going to look now at another case about אשרה
Asherah wood. דתנן, d'tenan, we taught in a משנה: Mishnah: נטל הימנה
עצים, natal himenah etzim, you took from an אשרה Asherah tree some
wood, some sticks. אסורין בהנאה, assurin b'hana'ah, you can't derive benefit from
them. No חידוש chiddush there. הסיק בהן את התנור, hisik bahen et
hatannur, let's say you used those sticks to fire up an oven.
חדש יותץ, chadash yutatz, ישן יוצן. yashan yutzan. So there it goes,
exactly what we said that we're trying, the position we're trying to
identify. You fired up an oven with איסורי הנאה. issurei hana'ah. If
it's a new oven, you have to destroy it. You can no
longer use that oven. If it's an old oven, then you just
wait for the fire to die down. אף בו את הפת, af
bo et hapat, and if you baked bread with this firewood, whether
an old or new oven, even an old oven, אסורין בהנאה, assurin
b'hana'ah, the bread is forbidden in benefit. נתערבה באחרות, nitarva b'acherot, who
says?
Now it's just תנא קמא.
Tana Kamma. Right. נתערבה באחרות, nitarva b'acherot, and right, the position we
had in our case by the ערלה Orlah of רבי, Rebbi, here
it's stated as a סתם stam position. נתערבה באחרות, nitarva b'acherot, this
loaf of bread that you now cannot eat because it has the
שבח עצים, shevach etzim, it had the benefit of the wood, if
it got mixed up with other loaves of bread, ואחרות באחרות, v'acherot
b'acherot, and then those loaves got mixed up with other ones. So
your one loaf fell into ten loaves, then one of those ten
loaves fell into another ten loaves. Okay, so you could say it's
a ספק ספיקא, sfeik sfeika, it's רוב, rov, it's ביטול, bittul, but
by עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah we're completely strict. So it says: כולן
אסורין בהנאה, kulan assurin b'hana'ah, everything is forbidden in benefit. Not just
this loaf, but any multiple types of mixes that it gets into,
it's all forbidden in benefit. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says in that case: יוליך הנאה לים המלח, yolichesh
hana'ah l'Yam HaMelach, maybe after it gets mixed up the first time,
maybe the second time, what you do is you take a coin,
a dollar that's worth whatever the value of the bread and you
throw it in the ocean and somehow that's a symbolic thing, because
obviously that doesn't really do anything, but symbolically that shows I'm losing
the benefit I will get now by eating the bread because I'm
throwing it away. I would have benefited a dollar from that loaf,
I'm throwing away a dollar, now I can get benefit. Would you
take one of the breads? No, you don't take one of the
breads.
You could have said that.
In other words, I know, I understand. אמרו לו אין פדיון לעבודה
זרה, amru lo ein pidyon l'Avodah Zarah, they said to him, you
don't redeem עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. Now obviously רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
agrees you don't really transfer the איסור issur to this coin. This
is some
ritual in a case where he feels maybe it would be too
extreme to continue to say it's forbidden, he allows this ritual as
a way of making it permissible. That's a fascinating idea. We're not
going to focus on that, okay? When we learn עבודה זרה, Avodah
Zarah, we'll talk about it. Why doesn't he
say? I don't know,
maybe it's איבוד אוכלים. ibud ochlim. Right now, what's relevant to us
is that we have a משנה Mishnah here that, bracketing the debate
of throwing the coin into the ocean, everybody agrees that not only
can you not eat the bread, which was רבי's Rebbi position, but
you have to destroy the oven, which is the position we're trying
to identify. Now, you could have said that it's the חכמים Chachamim
of רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, it's this whole משנה, Mishnah, but we
want a named תנא. Tana. So since רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer name
appeared, we hinge it on רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. But really what
the גמרא Gemara is saying is this משנה Mishnah in עבודה זרה,
Avodah Zarah, whoever is the author of this משנה Mishnah together with
רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, they are of the opinion that you cannot
use the oven. And that's very clear. זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh
gorem is a problem, you cannot use the oven. So the גמרא
Gemara says: one minute, maybe you can't make the comparison.
אימור דשמעת ליה לרבי אליעזר, eimur d'shamat lei l'Rabbi Eliezer, when did
we hear this case that the oven is a problem that רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and the תנא קמא Tana Kamma says it? בעבודה
זרה, b'Avodah Zarah, that's by עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, דחמיר איסורא, d'chamir
issura, that we know it's very strict. I mean, this case about
אחרים באחרים acherim b'acherim and עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah is never בטל,
batel, you know, there's a lot of stringencies we apply to עבודה
זרה. Avodah Zarah. So that's why we would say that that's an
issue. אבל בשאר איסורין שבתורה, aval b'sha'ar issurin shebaTorah, but by other
איסורין issurin of the תורה, Torah, מי שמעת ליה, mi shamat lei,
when did you ever hear him say this about other איסורין שבתורה?
issurin shebaTorah? I should mention by the way that in this discussion
of זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh gorem and I'm always afraid to
mention these things because I don't want to start a discussion, but
I will tell you, the whole issue of... buying fresh milk and
fresh eggs on פסח Pesach, *Pesach* because of concern that the cow
ate some feed which was חמץ chametz *Chametz* and then that's somehow
contributing to the production of the milk or to the production of
the eggs or whatnot. So a lot of people have a חומרא
*chumra* to buy all of their milk and eggs before פסח *Pesach*.
Rav Moshe says, you know, he it's based on a certain גמרא
Gemara. *Gemara* and Rav Moshe basically says that גמרא Gemara *Gemara* whatever
concerns that גמרא Gemara *Gemara* had about זה וזה גורם zeh vezeh
gorem *zeh va'zeh gorem* etc. I mean my god the feed it
all gets transformed and you know it's not so you know is
it really the same thing at all? Anyway Rav Moshe says the
concerns that this חומרא *chumra* is based on is from a discussion
around עבודה זרה avodah zarah, *Avodah Zarah*. So there it's we might
be more strict but technically says it's really not an issue and
Rav Moshe says in principle it's not a problem by חמץ *Chametz*.
So I just mention it because it's a great application a potential
application of זה וזה גורם zeh vezeh gorem *zeh va'zeh gorem* and
Rav Moshe makes exactly this distinction that you can't assume that חומרות
*chumras* we have about that by עבודה זרה avodah zarah. *Avodah Zarah*
apply elsewhere and that's what the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* is saying here.
So even if we're strict by the oven by עבודה זרה avoda
zara, *Avodah Zarah* doesn't mean that we hold that position elsewhere. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no. Rav Moshe says look in principle
you're right you could make that distinction but אלא אם כן *ella
im kein* אמרת רמייה *amrat ramyaye* if we don't say it's that
משנה Mishna, *Mishnah* in עבודה זרה avoda zara *Avodah Zarah* and that
Rabbi Eliezer and his colleague who are you going to throw it
on? Meaning we have to we have to identify somebody who's of
this position and we have the exact same position in עבודה זרה
avoda zara *Avodah Zarah*. So even though if in principle it could
be to distinguish the cases we don't we need a תנא *Tanna*
who is the תנא *Tanna* that's of that's the author of this
position by ערלה orlah *Orlah*? So we have to associate it with
someone. We're going to assume that that distinction does not hold and
that the author of it is Rabbi Eliezer and whoever his colleague
here is in עבודה זרה *Avodah Zarah*. ועוד אינא *ve'od ena* not
only that not only just logically we need to you know find
a position but הא תניא בהדיא *ha tanya behedya* we have a
ברייתא braita, *Braita* that spells it out explicitly. Here's the ברייתא braita,
*Braita* וכן היה *vechen haya* Rabbi Eliezer אוסר *oser* בכל איסורין שבתורה
*bechol issurin shebaTorah*. We have a ברייתא braita *Braita* that says that
don't Rabbi Eliezer's position is not just about עבודה זרה *Avodah Zarah*
actually again it's not Rabbi Eliezer it's Rabbi Eliezer and the תנא
קמא *Tanna Kamma* and that they says it by all things that
are forbidden in benefit that the oven would have to be destroyed
זה וזה גורם zeh vezeh gorem? *zeh va'zeh gorem* would be a
problem.
You have to assume that that one line is taken from this
same context I mean it's just a line I know.
Also it's a problem because it isn't Rabbi Eliezer who's אוסר *oser*
in this משנה *Mishnah* in עבודה זרה *Avodah Zarah* it's Rabbi Eliezer
who's מתיר *mattir* he's more lenient than the תנא קמא *Tanna Kamma*.
Right. So it is pretty interesting. All right so now the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says like this. So we find we said probably this
Rabbi Eliezer by עבודה זרה *Avodah Zarah*. אמר אביי *Amar Abaye*. Abaye
said אם תמצא לומר *im timtzei lomar* זה וזה גורם zeh vezeh
gorem *zeh va'zeh gorem* אסור assur, *assur*. Now Abaye is going to
really be making what is just a I think a restatement of
what we said before. If we assume that as a general rule
זה וזה גורם zeh vezeh gorem. *zeh va'zeh gorem* is אסור assur
*assur* right in other cases by תרומה *Terumah* by whatever then Rebbi
היינו *hiynu* Rabbi Eliezer then Rebbi who says the bread is אסור
assur *assur* would be saying the would would say the same as
Rabbi Eliezer would also say the oven is אסור assur *assur* meaning
this just restating what we said before. We know Rebbi says that
even after you bake the bread the bread remains a problem to
continue to eat the bread is to continue to derive benefit. Okay
but he said it might not apply to an oven because that's
a זה וזה גורם zeh vezeh gorem. *zeh va'zeh gorem*. Abaye says
fine but if the הלכה halacha *halacha* is זה וזה גורם zeh
vezeh gorem, *zeh va'zeh gorem* is אסור *assur* then the Rebbi that
said the bread is אסור *assur* would say the oven is אסור
*assur*. ואם תמצא לומר *ve'im timtzei lomar* זה וזה גורם ze v'ze
gorem, *zeh va'zeh gorem* מותר mutar, *mutar*. And if the rule is
that זה וזה גורם ze v'ze gorem. *zeh va'zeh gorem* is okay
is allowed so והכא משום דיש שבח עצים בפת mishum d'yesh shevach
eitzim b'pas. *vehacha mishum de'yesh shvach eitzim be'pas* and here the reason
of Rebbi is that the benefit of the wood still is in
the bread and you can't eat the bread okay but he would
not say that the oven is a problem because that would be
a זה וזה גורם zeh va-zeh gorem, *zeh va'zeh gorem*. So let's
talk about things other than the bread and other than the oven.
Now we were working within Rebbi. Bread no good that's a single
it's only coming from the bread. Oven okay cause it's the oven
plus the fire. So let's talk about other things. הני קדרות וכוסות
וצלוחיות *hani kderot vechosot vetzluchiyot*. If you have plates and cups and
bowls אסירי *assiri* made out of wood of איסורי הנאה isurei hana'ah,
*issurei hana'ah*. So is that like the bread or is that like
the oven? Are you getting is it one
this is a new oven?
You no you took wood you didn't use an oven at all
you took wood of איסורי הנאה isurei hana'ah. *issurei hana'ah* and you
made a cup out of it you made a plate out of
it.
So
it changes לגמרי *legamrei*. What? Maybe something new?
No that's not that's not new you'd have to turn it into
ashes to make to make it new. Oh I'm sorry I'm sorry
no no I jumped ahead I jumped ahead we're not talking about
you made it out of wood you were right I'm sorry I
was jumping ahead to another case. You took clay I'm sorry you
took clay
plates and cups and
whatever and you used the oven as a kiln and you fired
them in the oven this was with wood
this was the new oven.
No forget the oven you just used fire from wood that was
איסורי הנאה hana'ah, *issurei hana'ah* and you used this to fire up
these plates and cups ceramics ceramics okay so can you bake can
according to Rebbi that says you can't benefit from the bread. Can
you benefit from these? What do you think? Can you use the
plate? Can you use the cup?
Well you're eating the bread, but here with the bread, with the
cup you're putting something else on it, so it's going to stay
removed from that.
So let's take a look at what the גמרא Gemara says, okay?
So he says those are אסורי. assuri. Those are forbidden. So why?
Because presumably he treats those like the bread. The bread you- the
bread benefited from the fire from the wood and it's going straight
into your mouth. So you're- it's only one thing contributing. It's indirect,
but it's one thing. The plate benefited from the fire. It was
fired up, and you're using it, putting your food on it. You're
using it. Okay. The oven, however, is only used together with the
fire. That's going to be the distinction.
Okay. כי פליגי בתנור ובקדירה. Ki pligi betanur uvekedeirah. The issue that
רבי Rebbi and רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer disagree with is the oven
and a pot, okay? Now, למאן דאמר זה וזה גורם אסור אסור.
le-man de-amar zeh vezeh gorem assur assur. If זה וזה גורם is
a problem, that's a problem, because two things are contributing. למאן דאמר
זה וזה גורם מותר שרי, le-man de-amar zeh vezeh gorem mutar shari,
but if two things contributing are okay, שרי. shari. That's okay. Now
again, you're noticing that it's not so obvious. Why is a pot
okay? I mean, doesn't the food go in the pot? You know,
isn't the pot the same way I use a plate? I use
a pot, right? So why is the pot considered זה וזה גורם
and the plate considered not a זה וזה גורם? And the basic
answer is is that- well let's take a look. You'll see in
the next line in the גמרא. Gemara
איכא דאמרי, Ika de-amrei, some say, אפילו למאן דאמר זה וזה גורם
מותר, afilu le-man de-amar zeh vezeh gorem mutar, even if זה וזה
גורם is מותר, mutar. you can distinguish between a pot and an
oven. קדירה אסורה, Kedeirah asurah, the pot is forbidden. Why?
דקבלה בישולה מקמי דניתן עצים דהתירא, de-kablah bishulah mikamei de-nitan eitzim de-heteira,
because you put the food in the pot and you're using the
pot before you've lit the fire. So the גמרא's Gemara saying is
like this: use is like- using something is like getting הנאה, hana'ah,
using something is like getting הנאה, hana'ah right? So eating the bread
is obviously- that's obvious הנאה hana'ah and it's indirect הנאה from the
wood. Using the plate, using the cup is a type of benefit.
It's directly, physically I'm using them, I'm getting some use out of
that, and that's also indirectly getting the benefit from the wood.
Using the pot is an interesting question. At what stage do I
use the pot? If I am making my stew and I'm putting
the- the water in and the chicken in and the carrots, have
I used the pot yet? Or am I really only using it
once I put it on the fire? If I really only use
it once I put it on the fire, then I'm not- it's
not the only thing that is sort of helping me do what
I'm doing. It's the pot plus the fire and it's זה וזה
גורם. Okay? And the גמרא Gemara. in these two לשונות leshonos makes-
has that debate. According to one, you're- you only use the pot
in principle with the fire. Everything else was like prep. But the
using is when you put it on the fire and it's זה
וזה גורם. You're not only using it. And according to the others
it says no, by an oven, the fire's already going, and then
when you put the bread in, when you're using it, you're using
two things together. But by the pot, you put the stuff in
before you put it on the fire, and therefore you wind- you're
using the pot by itself, and therefore the pot is a problem.
Okay, so that is the point of the גמרא, Gemara very fascinating
within זה וזה גורם, when do we consider it that you're using
something and deriving benefit?
You're using it by itself. Bread and plates and whatever you use
by themselves, an oven you use with the fire, and the pot
is debated because its ultimate use is with the fire, but there
is a stage where you're using it by itself.
דבר שלא נעשה, Davar shelo na'asah, if you put the pot empty
on the fire and then put the food in it, according to
everyone...
then that would be מותר. mutar, That would be מותר, mutar. yes,
exactly. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, hold on,
I just want to just check one thing in רש"י. Rashi. If
you
put an empty pot on the fire, then put...
exactly.
Okay fine, let's keep on reading. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this. אמר רב יוסף אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל. Amar Rav Yosef
amar Rav Yehudah amar Shmuel. תנור שהסיקו בקליפי ערלה או בקשים של
כלאי הכרם. Tanur she-hisiko be-klipi orlah o be-kashim shel kil'ei hakerem.
So now we've got this oven that you have fired up with
these- איסורי הנאה, this wood of איסורי הנאה. חדש יוצת ישן יוצן.
Chadash yutzat yashan yutzan.
Okay, that's what we said before.
האפה בו את הפת, afah bo et hapat, if you baked bread,
רבי אומר הפת מותרת, Rebbi omer hapat muteret,
רבי Rebbi says now we're reversing who says what. רבי Rebbi says
the bread is permissible. וחכמים אומרים הפת אסורה, Ve-Chachamim omrim hapat asurah,
and the חכמים Chachamim say the bread is forbidden. Okay, so we
reversed. In our ברייתא, braita רבי Rebbi said it was forbidden and
the חכמים Chachamim said permissible. In this ברייתא, baraita. it's reversed. So
the גמרא Gemara, says והתניא איפכא, ve-hatanya ipcha, didn't our original ברייתא
baraita: have the positions reversed? רבי Rebbi said forbidden and חכמים Chachamim
said permissible by the bread? So the גמרא Gemara says שמואל איפכא
תני. Shmuel ipcha tani. Yeah fine, שמואל's Shmuel ברייתא braita had the
reversed version. ואיבעית אימא, Ve-iba'it eima, now the גמרא Gemara says a
more radical answer. If you want I could say, בעלמא קסבר. be-alma
kasavar. שמואל Shmuel הלכה כרבי מחבירו. halacha k'rabbi me'haveiro.
Really, here's the issue. שמואל Shmuel had our ברייתא. רבי Rabbi said
it was forbidden, חכמים Hachamim said it was permissible. But now שמואל's
Shmuel got a problem because he generally holds we rule like רבי
Rabbi when he argues with one colleague ולא מחביריו, v'lo me'haveirav, not
when he argues with more than one colleague. And here he's arguing
with the חכמים. Hachamim. So if שמואל Shmuel were to apply his
general rule and he has our גרסא girsa that רבי Rabbi says
it's אסור, we would say according to the חכמים, Hachamim, it's מותר.
muttar
But ובא האפילו מחביריו, u'v'ha afilu me'haveirav, here שמואל Shmuel happens to
hold that רבי Rabbi is right and therefore it's forbidden. So he's
got a problem. He says, I want to פסקן pasken like רבי
Rabbi that it's forbidden, but people are not going to believe me
because they're going to say, what do you mean? According to שמואל,
Shmuel, you say that we have to go like the majority opinion
against רבי. Rabbi. וסבר, v'savar, so he figured, here's what I'll do.
אשנייה איפכא, ashniye ipcha, I'll teach it in reverse כי היכי, ki
heichi, I'll flip it דניגמרו רבנן לאיסורא. d'nigmaru rabanan l'issura.
The majority position will be the rabbis, and therefore people won't give
me a hard time. So it's quite shocking, right? In order, I
mean, whatever happened to intellectual honesty? Whatever, then misrepresenting תורה. Torah. Yeah,
I really don't know what to say about that. It's a quite
shocking and disturbing גמרא. Gemara I will say, though, that you have
something somewhat like that the גמרא Gemara says about רבי יהודה הנשיא.
Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi. The גמרא Gemara actually says that, you know, רבי
Rabbi sometimes would take a דעת יחיד da'at yachid and make it
the סתם stam opinion in the משנה, the anonymous opinion, so that
it would be the authoritative one. But even there you're not misrepresenting.
You know, you're taking a דעת יחיד da'at yachid and you're giving
it weight by presenting it as an anonymous opinion. But here, it's
actually גמרא Gemara saying that שמואל Shmuel would actually misrepresent so that
people would accept his פסק, psak, which is quite shocking. I really
don't know what to say about that. Okay, so now we move
on. That is the issue about the oven, a very important גמרא,
Gemara both about the principle about זה וזה גורם, two contributors, and
the idea about—and I want to sort of point out because this
is what we're going to continue
on—that יש שבח עצים בפת yesh shevach eitzim b'pas is a חידוש.
chiddush. Remember, the חכמים Hachamim say you can eat the פת. pas.
Not everybody says forget זה וזה גורם. That was interesting: the oven
and the fire, the פת pas versus the plates, when is it
one thing, when is it two things. But there's another issue here
before you get to that: the bread itself. And the חכמים Hachamim
say you can eat the bread, okay, because it's not so obvious
once you bake the bread that to eat the bread is to
consider to continue to derive benefit. You could say once you bake
the bread you've derived your benefit, end of story; now if you
eat it, you know, the wood no longer exists. So there's a
חידוש chiddush in saying יש שבח עצים בפת, yesh shevach eitzim b'pas,
that the benefit is still considered present and you're still deriving benefit
when you continue to eat the bread.
Is there a practical הלכה application that we have from all this?
Yeah, I mean, I gave you one was the whole thing about
milk on פסח, but a lot of these things are applied להלכה.
l'halacha. Let's take a look now as the גמרא Gemara discusses this
issue, the prior issue of יש שבח עצים. yesh shevach eitzim. בשלמא
גבי גחלים דברי הכל פת מותרת. Bishlama gabei gechalim divrei hakol pas
muteres. So it's going to the second part of this ברייתא: if
these things have already turned to coal, then it's no longer considered
to be ערלה orlah or כלאי הכרם. kilayim. Like I said, ישרפו
אפרן מותר, yisrefu afram mutar, and everybody says that the bread is
permissible. So רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, so you
had the position of רב יהודה Rav Yehuda שמואל, Shmuel, רב חייא
בר אשי אמר רבי יוחנן. Rav Chiya bar Ashi amar Rabbi Yochanan.
חד אמר, chad amar, one says of these two אמוראים, Amoraim, one
says לא שנו אלא בגחלים עוממות. lo shanu ela b'gechalim omemot. When
is it that everybody says it's permissible? When they're like, you know,
coals that are basically essentially extinct, like petering out; it's really total
black charcoal.
אבל גחלים לוחשות, aval gechalim lochashot, if they're still whispering, you know,
they still got a nice fire going—yes, they're coals, but glowing, right?
I mean, literally it means like whispering—you understand what it means, like
there's
a fire going on there. So then אסורין, assurin, it's still a
problem because they're still burning off of, you know, existing wood, it's
not all charcoal. And if רבי Rabbi says it's a problem, he
would say even these types of coals are a problem. וחד אמר,
v'chad amar, the other says אפילו גחלים לוחשות נמי מותרות. afilu gechalim
lochashot nami mutarot. No, even if they're at this stage of whispering,
it's still permissible, in this case even רבי Rabbi would say it's
permissible, which is surprising. So let's take a look. גמרא Gemara says
like this: בשלמא למאן דאמר לוחשות אסורין, bishlama l'man d'amar lochashot assurin,
I get the position that says that these whispering coals are forbidden
when they're still burning off of some wood משום דיש שבח עצים
בפת. Normally it's אסור because the wood is contributing to the
bread and therefore even out—even in this stage when they're—when they're whispering,
there's still a little wood there that's being burnt and that's contributing
to the bread and it's a problem. אלא למאן דאמר אפילו לוחשות
מותרות, ela l'man d'amar afilu lochashot mutarot, but if at this stage
it's permissible, so the גמרא Gemara says פת דאסיר דיש שבח עצים
בפת לרבי היכי משכחת לה? pas d'assir d'yesh shevach eitzim b'pas l'Rabbi
heichi mashkachas lei? What's the case where רבי Rabbi would actually say
that it's a problem? I mean, if it's okay when the coals
are at this stage, when is it a problem? So the גמרא
Gemara says אמר רב פפא כשאבוקה כנגדו, amar Rav Pappa k'she'avuka k'negdo,
when the flame is opposite it. What seems to be the גמרא
Gemara understands is that the normal way you would do it is
that you would have, you would get the fire to a... The
state where it's coals and then you would bake it over the
coals. So the גמרא Gemara's says, so when is there ever a
scenario that it's a problem? So the גמרא Gemara says, no, the
scenario when it's a problem is when you have a live flame,
when it's not like the flame is low and buried in the
coals when you have a real big fire, that's when it's considered
that the wood is actually contributing. Now I have to tell you
that it's hard to see the גמרא Gemara just was asking like
what would be the case? But really the follow-up question is what's
the conceptual distinction? Right, why when it's a big raging fire do
we say the wood is contributing to the to the bread and
why when it's a small whispering flame that's low do we say
it's not? I mean it's already burnt. Well, but it's still there's
still presumably the difference between לוחשות luchashot and עוממות. omemot. Maybe I'm
wrong about this, is that the לוחשות luchashot there's still some actually
unburnt wood that's still burning. That's what I'm assuming. If that's not
true, if it's completely charcoal, then it should seem obvious that לוחשות
luchashot are permissible, right? So it's like I don't get it, right?
If it's completely charcoal, I don't get the position that says לוחשות
luchashot is a problem. Who cares if there's a good flame or
not a good flame if it's already completely charcoal? And if it's
not completely charcoal and there's a little bit of wood, then I
don't get the distinction between לוחשות luchashot and
אבוקה כנגדו. avuka kenegdo. It's wood, it's wood, who cares if it's
98% charcoal and 2% of the wood is burning, unless maybe you
say it's a זה וזה גורם, in that case some of the
benefit is coming from the charcoal and some from the wood. Okay,
so I don't really get it though. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this. Okay, מכלל, michlal, so from this we can
infer דרבנן דפליגי עליה, de-Rabbanan de-pligi alei, that the רבנן Rabbanan that
argue on רבי, Rebbe, שרי אפילו כשאבוקה כנגדו, shari afilu kshe-avuka kenegdo,
would allow even when you have a nice big fire. So why?
Now what's the logic for that? Now again, what I would have
said, which is not what the גמרא Gemara is saying is, is
that they would have said obviously you can't bake bread on that
flame, you're getting benefit from the wood, but they just would say
if you baked the bread then you're over and done with and
then to eat the bread is not a continuing is not does
not is not an ongoing problem. But the גמרא Gemara understands the
רבנן Rabbanan to say a more radical position. That the רבנן Rabbanan
would actually say you're allowed to bake the bread on that flame.
Why? Because if you think about it, fire is created when the
wood is consumed. So even if you have a stick of wood
here, the flame you have here, you have wood down here but
the flame you have here is coming from wood that's been destroyed,
from the consumption of the wood. So the גמרא Gemara understands that
the רבנן Rabbanan that say the bread is permissible don't only say
בדיעבד bedi'avad the bread is permissible, they would say you could cook
on that fire because that fire was created from already destroyed wood.
So then there is never, what? So that's the גמרא's Gemara answer.
So then it never allowed to bake something with
forbidden wood? Right, because
there's no such thing as cooking with wood, it's
done by the time you're benefit
from the fire.
Exactly. So that's how the גמרא Gemara understands the רבנן. Rabbanan. Not
just the bread is permissible but you can even bake with this
fire. So therefore the גמרא Gemara says one minute, the גמרא Gemara
says אלא עצים דאיסורא רבנן היכי משכחת להו? ela etzim de-issura Rabbanan
heichi mashkachat lahu? So how would you ever have a case of
wood that's forbidden in benefit, meaning how could you ever transgress with
forbidden wood according to the רבנן? Rabbanan? Never any case of making
a fire. So אמר רמי בר חמא בששיפא, Amar Rami bar Chama
beshashifa, with a stool. So like a one-word answer. You make a
chair out of the wood. Okay? You if you want to transgress
with forbidden wood, it's not by making a fire, then you've already
destroyed the wood. It's by making a chair, making some object out
of the wood. That's how you would actually be able to transgress
with forbidden wood according to the רבנן.
Rabbanan. Why can't they use my חמץ and burn it and bake
something on it?
What? According to the חכמים Hachamim presumably you can.
Wasn't there a סתם משנה stam mishna that you can't לא יסיק
בו תנור וכירה? lo yasik bo tannur ve-khirayim?
Yeah, but that was that presumably according to this גמרא Gemara that
presumably is שיטת רבי. shittat Rebbe. I agree it's radical. I would
have said רבי's Rebbe's position is only post facto allowing the bread,
it certainly sounds like everybody assumes you're not supposed to use it.
But that was what you said before. We said no it was
according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that we're
saying this. And we said it's a פשיטא. pshita. Yeah, we said
פשיטא pshita first of all, which means sounds like it's a דעת
das of everybody. And you said oh yeah, though it is פשוט
pashut even according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says מצותו בשריפה, mitzvaso
bi-sreifa, even then they still don't allow it. Right. But if we're
saying that's according to רבי Rebbe that doesn't seem to you know
you mean just why the גמרא Gemara said פשיטא pshita before. Yeah,
I agree it's very strange. It's very strange the assumption of the
גמרא Gemara that not just בדיעבד bedi'avad the bread is מותר but
לכתחילה le-chatchila you could do it is a hard position to believe
on its own and also you're right it doesn't really fit into
the סתם משנה. stam mishna. The סתם משנה stam mishna sounds like
there begins to be issues when you talk about eating the bread.
It assumes that everybody assumes you can't actually use it לכתחילה. le-chatchila.
Yeah, I agree. Alright let's see now let's at least get to
the two dots. The גמרא says like this.
Okay. בעי מיניה רמי בר חמא מרב חסדא. Bei minei Rami bar
Chama me-Rav Chisda. רמי בר חמא Rami bar Chama asked רב חסדא.
Rav Chisda. תנור שהסיקו בעצי הקדש. Tannur she-hisiku bi-atzei hekdesh. So let's
say we're not dealing with ערלה orlah or כלאים, kilayim, another thing
that's אסור בהנאה, assur be-hana'ah, הקדש. hekdesh. Okay? ואפה בו את הפת,
ve-afa bo es ha-pas, and you baked bread. דרבנן דשרו בקמייתא מאי?
De-Rabbanan de-sharu bi-kamaisa mai?
The Rabbis that normally say the bread is okay what would they
say if it was if it was הקדש? hekdesh? done with wood
of הקדש. hekdesh. So אמר ליה הפת אסורה. amar lei ha-pat assurah.
Oh, the bread is forbidden. So מה בין זו לערלה? ma bein
zo le-orlah? Now he obviously must have thought there was a difference
because he bothered to ask the question. So he says, why, so
what is that difference? Why would הקדש hekdesh be different? So אמר
רבא amar Rava הכי השתא. hachi hashta. What's the comparison? Of course
it's different. ערלה orlah בטילה במאתים. beteila be-matayim. ערלה is batel one
in two hundred. הקדש hekdesh אפילו באלף לא בטיל. afilu be-elef lo
batil.
הקדש hekdesh is never בטל. batel. So this is like echoing the
Gemara before about עבודה זרה, which means, now there's not a logic
between saying not בטל batel and and the bread is forbidden. Because
the bread is forbidden is not a ביטול bitul scenario. It's much
more of a point that since הקדש hekdesh isn't בטל, batel, you
see we're very strict about הקדש. hekdesh. So if we're very strict
about it, we'll be so strict to say that even the bread
will be forbidden even if normally it's okay. It's like almost exactly
parallel to what the Gemara before said about עבודה זרה. There could
be a general rule, but by categories that are more strict, we'll
be more strict as well, even if there's no particular direct logic
why that should be true. Right? We're just gonna generally be more
off-limits, more strict, we'll be more strict about a lot of things.
Okay. אלא אמר רבא, ela amar Rava, so Rava said, אי קשיא
לי הא קשיא. ei kashya li ha kashya. If there was ever
a question about making a distinction, here's what the question should have
been. והלא מעל המסיק? ve-halo maal ha-masik? How could the bread be
a problem? As soon as you burn that firewood, you're being עובר
over on מעילה, me'ilah, right? Because מעילה me'ilah is either through benefiting
or misuse, clearly taking הקדש hekdesh firewood and putting it in your
oven is misuse and appropriating it.
Misuse and appropriating, the moment you take it away, right?
Anyway, and if you're
מועל, mo'el, then the wood stops being הקדש. hekdesh. The act of
מעילה me'ilah makes the object חולין. chullin. It stops being הקדש. hekdesh.
So how could you transgress by burning, you know, how could the
bread be forbidden because yes, you did a transgression of מעילה, me'ilah,
but then it stopped being הקדש hekdesh and the bread should be
okay. So והלא מעל המסיק, ve-halo maal ha-masik, the one who made
the fire is מועל. mo'el. וכל היכא דמעל המסיק, ve-chol heicha de-maal
ha-masik, whenever the one who made the fire is מועל, mo'el, whenever
somebody is מועל, mo'el, נפקו להו לחולין, nafku lehu le-chullin, the object
becomes חולין. chullin. Now, it's only objects that have monetary sort of
value as הקדש. hekdesh. Something like a קרבן korban or כלי שרת,
kli sharet, that would retain, that's about its identity. But something that's
been sanctified for its value, once you've done מעילה, me'ilah, it loses
its הקדש. hekdesh. So how could there be a problem with the
bread? So אמר רב פפא amar Rav Pappa הכא בעצי שלמים עסקינן.
hacha be-atzei shelamim askinan. We're talking about bread that's been sanctified to
use the money to buy a שלמים. shelamim. I'm not bread, but
wood that's been sanctified to use that money. Why does that matter?
Because you say it again? What'd you say again? You sanctified wood
and you said, I'm going to, with the proceeds of this wood,
I will buy a שלמים. shelamim. Now the reason we introduce a
שלמים shelamim is because a שלמים shelamim is the one קרבן korban
that there's, or the one הקדש hekdesh thing there's no מעילה me'ilah
on because the שלמים shelamim you're going to eat and it's not
going to, it's considered yours basically. It's not considered God's. Only the
אימורין imurin are God's and only after you do the זריקת הדם.
zerikat ha-dam. So therefore if the bread, if the wood has the
sanctity of a שלמים, shelamim, there won't be מעילה me'ilah on the
wood and therefore the wood will remain אסור even after misuse. It'll
remain הקדש. hekdesh.
Wait, but they're the קרבנות korbanot that are eaten in part.
Yes, but when you eat a חטאת, chatat, a חטאת chatat is
considered, the Gemara says משלחן גבוה קא
זכו. mi-shulchan gavoah ka zachu. It's God's קרבן korban that the כהנים
kohanim are eating, it's God's that the כהנים kohanim are eating, you're
not eating it as if it's yours, which is also this principle
like הכהנים אוכלים ובעלים מתכפרים. ha-kohanim ochlim u-be'alim mitchaprim. The כהנים kohanim
are considered like sort of a part of the בית המקדש, Beit
Ha-Mikdash, they're not their own person.
הקדוש ברוך הוא Ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu is serving them from his meal.
Exactly, exactly. So the Gemara says ואליבא דרבי יהודה, ve-aliba de-Rabbi Yehuda,
and this is and this is similar like or following the position
of Rabbi Yehuda, דאמר הקדש בשוגג מתחלל, de-amar hekdesh be-shogeg mitchalel, who
says if you accidentally misuse הקדש, hekdesh, then it is desecrated,
meaning then it becomes חולין. chullin. במזיד אינו מתחלל. be-mezid eino mitchalel.
Again somewhat ironic. If you willfully desecrated הקדש, hekdesh, you know,
misused הקדש, hekdesh, it does not, it does not become חולין. chullin.
Why is that? במזיד מאי טעמא לא? be-mezid mai ta'ama lo? Why
by במזיד be-mezid does it not? כיון דלאו בר מעילה הוא keivan
de-lav bar me'ilah hu because you only bring a קרבן korban of
מעילה me'ilah בשוגג. be-shogeg. Now, you could still say you transgressed the
prohibition of מעילה me'ilah במזיד, be-mezid, but he says since you only
bring a קרבן korban of מעילה me'ilah בשוגג, be-shogeg, מזיד mezid you
did is not, does not have the full status of this category
of מעילה me'ilah because there's no
קרבן, korban, לא נפיק לחולין, lo nafik le-chullin, it doesn't go out
to חולין. chullin. So if that's true about מזיד, mezid, which is
an extreme case, שלמים נמי. shelamim nami. Now, you could have just
as שלמים shelamim as well, כיון דלאו בר מעילה נינהו, keivan de-lav
bar me'ilah ninhu, you never, you don't bring a קרבן, korban, שלמים
shelamim is not considered מעילה me'ilah because it's basically considered
yours, לא נפיק לחולין, lo nafik le-chullin, it does not lose its
status even in misuse. So it's not the misuse per se that
makes it stop being הקדש, hekdesh, it's the technical act of מעילה.
me'ilah. And therefore if something is technically not מעילה me'ilah even if
it's misused, it will remain הקדש. hekdesh. What would be a scenario?
Either מזיד, mezid, ironic, or שלמים. shelamim. Even though in both of
those cases it's misused, it— Since it's not מעילה, meilah, it continues
to be
הקדש. hekdesh. וכל היכא דמעל המעל מסיק נפקי לחולין. v'chol heicha d'ma'al
hama'al masik nafki le'chulin. Are you telling me whenever there's מעילה, meilah,
it goes out or if you burned wood, it goes out to
חולין? chulin? ותניא, v'tanya, and now we end with a ברייתא which
I mentioned at the
beginning: כל הנשרפין אפרן מותר, kol hanisrafin afaran mutar, anything that is
burned, the ashes are permissible, חוץ, chutz, with the exception of עצי
אשרה, atzei asherah, wood, okay, because it's עבודה זרה, whatever, ואפר הקדש.
v'afar hekdesh. So by the way, again, very nicely, the two strict
categories of about wood here is עבודה זרה and הקדש, hekdesh, like
we were saying. Those will be stricter with. But the גמרא says
דאפר הקדש לעולם אסור. d'afar hekdesh l'olam assur. האפר ha'afar of הקדש
hekdesh will be אסור even after you've burned it. So the גמרא
says I don't get it, same problem. Why is the ashes remain
forbidden? Once you've burned it, you've done מעילה, meilah, right? And then
the ashes should become permissible because you've done
מעילה. meilah. אמר רמי בר חמא כגון שנפלה דליקה מאליה בעצי הקדש.
amar Rami bar Chama k'gon shenafal daleka me'eleha b'atzei hekdesh. Who said
you did מעילה? meilah? Maybe a fire broke out in the wood.
So nobody did מעילה meilah and you have ashes. Doesn't mean מעילה
meilah was done. דליכא אינש דנימעל. d'leka inish d'nimal. Nobody did מעילה
meilah and nevertheless the ashes remain forbidden. ורב אשי אמר באותם שטעונים
גניזה. v'Rav Ashi amar be'osam shete'unim gniza. We're talking about ashes that
you didn't do מעילה. meilah. What are ashes you didn't do מעילה?
meilah? The ashes of תרומת הדשן, trumas hadeshen, that you have to
do גניזה, gniza, that you have to leave them there. This again
echoes a גמרא from a few days ago. דתניא ושמו, d'tanya v'samo,
you put the ashes בנחת, benachas, nicely, ושמו כולו, v'samo kulo, all
of it, ושמו שלא יפזר, v'samo shelo yifazer, it doesn't scatter. So
the גמרא says you can have ashes that were created not through
מעילה. meilah. Either a fire broke out or there was a מצוה,
mitzvah, you the ashes from the מזבח. mizbe'ach. There was no מעילה
meilah from the ashes from the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So the גמרא says
the conclusion of the גמרא is: yes, if you misuse הקדש, hekdesh,
sometimes that act will make it חולין, chulin, and then it'll be
permissible. But as a general rule, we're going to be more strict
about the wood of עבודה זרה and הקדש hekdesh than we will
by other things. Those ashes even as ashes will remain forbidden, and
even a type of זבזי גורן zivzei goren and using the bread
and all those types of things will be more strict in those
categories than our general rule.